Hello, and welcome to Lesson 5 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
你好 欢迎来到 Wolfram U 微积分入门的第五课
Our topic for today is the laws of limits. Let’s begin with a brief overview
我们今天的主题是极限定律 让我们从一个简短的课程概述开始
of today’s lesson. We learned in the previous lesson that using tables to find limits
在之前的课程中 我们学习了利用表格来计算极限
can be very tedious work. What we’ll do today is to set up some laws for limits
这是十分乏味的工作 今天我们将建立一些关于极限的法则
which will let us compute the same limits quite easily. To do that,
这些法则会使极限的计算变得十分简单 为了做到这一点
I’m going to use two example functions. The first one is called f. The second one is called g.
我会使用两个函数作为例子 第一个函数命名为 f 第二个命名为 g
f is 2x + 2, and g is 3Cos[x]/2. Those two functions are gonna serve as
f = 2x + 2 g = 3Cos[x]/2 这两个函数会在
our example functions in the first part of the lesson. Here are the plots of the functions.
课程的第一部分作为我们的示例函数 这是函数的图像
f is of course just a linear function, while g is a trigonometric function. Now if you look at the plots,
显然 f 是一个线性函数 而 g 是一个三角函数 如果观察一下这些图像
it’s clear that the limit of f is going to be 2 at 0, and the limit of g is going to be 3/2.
就会发现 f 在 0 处的极限为 2 g 在 0 处的极限为 3/2
Let’s confirm that with the Limit function. The limits are 2 and 3/2. You need to bear in mind
让我们用 Limit 函数确认一下 极限是 2 和 3/2 你需要记住
throughout today that f is this linear function, g is a trigonometric function
今天课程中的 f 代表这个线性函数 而 g 代表一个三角函数
and the limits are 2 and 3/2. With just that small piece of baggage,
并且它们的极限分别是 2 和 3/2 只要记住这一点
we can now begin our discussion of the laws of limits, and the first law called the sum law.
我们就可以开始关于极限法则的讨论 第一个法则是极限的加法法则
It says that the limit of a sum is the sum of the limits. For example, if you want to find
即 函数和的极限等于函数极限的和 举个例子 如果你想求
of f + g, you simply add 2 and 3/2 and get 7/2, and you can check that with the Limit function
f + g 的极限 只需要简单的把 2 和 3/2 相加得到 7/2 你可以用 Limit 函数检查一下
and get back just the same result. Here’s a plot of all three functions, f, g and f + g,
会得到相同的结果 这是三个函数 f g 和 f + g 的图像
and you can see quite clearly that f + g, which is right over here, has got the limit 7/2
可以十分清楚地看到 f + g 就在这儿 当 x 趋于 0 时
as x approaches 0. Now along with that, you can also say that the limit of a difference
取得极限值 7/2 你也可以说 函数差的极限
is going to be the difference of the limits. In our case, it’s going to be 2 − 3/2. That’s 1/2.
等于函数极限的差 在我们的例子中 函数极限的差为 2 − 3/2 即 1/2
You also have a scalar multiplication law, which let you multiply a constant by a function,
还有数乘法则 当你想求常数与一个函数乘积的极限
and then you simply do the limit of the function times that constant. If you want to find
只需要简单地把函数的极限与该常数相乘 例如想算
the limit of 3 * f[x], it’s just going to be 3 times the limit of f[x], so that’s 3 * 2 is 6, in this case.
3 * f[x] 的极限 只需用 3 乘 f[x] 的极限 那么就是 3 * 2 等于 6 在这个例子里
You’ve got the sum law, the difference law and the scalar multiplication law so far,
目前为止你已经有了极限的加法法则 减法法则和数乘法则
and to go on, let’s talk now about the product law, which says that the limit of a product
继续 让我们来讨论一下乘法法则 该定律表述为 函数乘积的极限
is the product of the limits. For example, if you want to find the limit of f  *g,
等于函数极限的乘积 举个例子 如果想求 f  *g 的极限
it’s just going to be 2 * 3/2. That’s 3. You can check that with Limit and get back
只需把 2 与 3/2 相乘 得 3 你可以用 Limit 检查一下 结果
just the same answer. Here’s a plot of all the three functions—f, g and f * g—
是相同的 这是三个函数 f, g and f * g 的图像
and you can see quite clearly that the limit of f * g is 3, exactly as we said earlier on.
十分清晰地可以看出 f * g 的极限是 3 确实如我们之前所言
Along with the product law, we also have the power law, which says that if you want to find
除了乘法法则 我们还有极限的幂法则 表述为 函数幂的极限
the limit for a power, then it is the power of the limit. For example, the limit of f^3
等于函数极限的幂 例如 f^3 的极限
is the cube of the limit of f, so 2^3 is 8, and therefore you get back 8 as the answer.
是 f 极限的立方 也就是 2^3 等于 8 因此 8 就是答案
Now you’ve got the sum law, the difference law, the scalar multiplication law,
现在你已经获得了加法法则 减法法则 数乘法则
the product law and the power law. As the next law for us, we take up the quotient law.
乘法法则以及幂法则 下一个法则是商法则
When you divide things can go wrong, but most of the time they don’t. The limit of a quotient is
当你做除法的时时可能会出错 但大多数时候不会出错 函数商的极限等于
the quotient of the limits, provided that the denominator does not have a limit of 0.
函数极限的商 条件是分母的极限不为零
In our case, f and g, you have the limit of f/g is just 4/3 because 2/(3/2) is 4/3.
我么的例子里 f/g 的极限就是 4/3 因为 2/(3/2) 是 4/3
Here is a plot of all the three functions, f, g and f/g. You can again see what is happening
这是三个函数  f g 和 f/g 的图像 你可以再次看到
that the answer is actually correct as guessed by us. There is a problem at π/2, though,
答案与我们的猜测一致 不过在 π/2 处出现了问题
because the value of g at π/2 is 0. Then we are in trouble because the limit of f/g
这是因为 g 在  π/2 的值是 0 于是我们有了麻烦 因为 f/g 的极限
at that point is just indeterminate. The quotient law is almost true, and it’s not true
在这一点是不确定的 商法则在大多数情况是正确的 但是
when the denominator is becoming 0 in any way.
当作为分母的函数极限为 0 时商法则就不再正确了
Okay. Some examples now of limits. If you have a polynomial, then you can quite easily
好吧 现在来看一些极限的例子 如果有一个多项式 那么可以很容易地
compute its limit, but to do that we need to access some facts. First of all, fact 1:
计算它的极限 但要做到这一点 我们需要了解一些事实 首先是事实 1：
the limit of a constant is a constant. Let’s check that. The limit of 5 will be 5,
常数的极限是一个常数 让我们来检验一下 5 的极限是 5
and the limit of 1/2 would be 1/2, et cetera. The limit of a constant is a constant,
1/2 的极限是 1/2 等等 常数的极限是常数
and the other fact is that the limit of the simple function x as x approaches a is just a.
第二个事实是 简单函数 x 在自变量 x 趋近于 a 时的值为 a
You just plug in a and get back the answer. Okay. Once you have just those two facts,
只需要取函数值 a 作为极限值即可 好 一旦你有了这两个事实
then you can work out the limit of any polynomial. For example, if you want to work out
就可以计算多项式的极限 例如 你想算
the limit of 2x^2 − 4x + 3, you simply plug in the values over there, and you get back
2x^2 − 4x + 3 在某一点的极限 只需简单的取多项式在那一点的值 就会得到
the answer at 4, for example.
在自变量取 4 时的极限
Okay. We now worked out the limit of a polynomial by substitution, and the question is
好了 我们通过代换得到了多项式的极限 问题是
what happens when you have a rational function?
当你遇到有理函数的时候呢?
Here is a rational function, and you want to find the limit of this function when x approaches −2.
这是有一个有理函数 并且你想算自变量 x 趋近于 -2 时的函数极限
Now when x is −2, there is no problem at all because the denominator is not 0.
现在 x 取值为 -2 这完全没有问题因为有理函数的分母不为 0
Here you have g is the numerator, h is the denominator of the rational function, and to find
这里 g 是有理函数的分子 h 是分母 为了
the limit of f as x approaches −2, you simply divide the limits of numerator and denominator,
为了得到当 x 趋近于 -2 时 f 的极限值 可以简单地用分子的极限除以分母的极限
and you get back the answer 10/13 whether you work out the limit directly or you work it out
得到的答案是 10/13 无论你直接计算极限 还是通过
by taking a quotient, like over here, or you simply work out a value of the function at −2.
取分子分母极限的商计算极限 或者直接取函数在 -2 处的值
Rational functions are almost as easy as polynomials in most cases. But to go on,
有理函数在大多数情况下几乎像多项式函数一样简单 不过接下来
I’ll give an example where things can go wrong. Here’s an example of a rational function,
我会给出一个出错的例子 这是一个有关有理函数的例子
but you want to find the limit at −1, and sure enough, there’s an issue over here
不过这次你想求函数在 -1 点的极限值 十分确定的是 这里是有问题的
because the denominator becomes 0. The denominator is 0 over here;
因为分母为 0 由于分母为 0
we cannot use a direct computation, so what we do is we factor the numerator
我们无法直接计算 所以我们将分子因式分解
and check that, in fact, we have a common factor of 1 + x. To cancel this common factor,
观察一下 事实上 我们有公因式 1 + x 消去公因子
we can use several functions. I’ll use Simplify over here, and that’ll get the function down to
我们可以调用多种函数 这里我用 Simplify 简化一下 得到函数的
its simplest possible form in which you can plug in the values, and you can see quite clearly
可能的最简形式 你可以直接使用这种形式取值 且十分清楚地看到
that the limit is −1 − 1. That’s −2, and that’s confirmed by the Limit function.
函数极限值为 −1 − 1 也就是 − 2 这是由极限函数证明的
Okay. That’s about rational functions, and now to go a step further, let’s talk about difference quotients,
好 这是关于有理函数的 现在更进一步 讨论一下差商
which are very closely related to all the previous ideas. Here is the difference quotient for
这与之前的想法非常接近 这是一个有理函数的差商
a rational function, and what you see over here is if you plot it, then it’s just a straight line.
你可以看到 如果将这个差商画出来 就是一条直线
What’s happening? Well, what’s happening is that although the h over here is 0 at h = 0,
发生了什么? 尽管分母在 h = 0 处的值为 0
there is a common factor, and to find the common factor, you can do an expansion
然而分子分母有公因子 为了找到这个公因子 你可以将其展开
and then do a kind of factoring and get the function down to its simplest possible form.
然后分解因式将函数化为最简形式
That function over there f, which looked difficult, is in fact just 4 + h.
所以这个函数 f 看起来很复杂 实际上就是 4 + h
Then what you can do is you can work out the limit of f as h approaches 0 and get the answer as 4.
然后 你需要做的就是计算 h 趋于 0 时函数 f 的极限 答案是 4
We have learned now that sometimes canceling factors is a really good idea.
我们认识到有时消去因式是一个很好的主意
Okay. Next, how about things like the absolute value function? Here’s the absolute value function.
好 下一步 如果是绝对值函数的情况呢? 这是一个绝对值函数
If I plot it, it’s kind of got a V shape, and when you are at 0 over here, then it’s clear that the limit is 0
如果我把它画出来 它是 V 形的 并且函数值在 0 处显然为 0
whether you approach from the left or the right. The left-hand limit and the right-hand limit
无论你从左侧还是右侧趋近 都会得到相同的结果 左极限和右极限
are both 0 from this picture. You can confirm that with Limit itself by doing a direction computation.
可以从图中看出都是 0 你可以直接计算证明这个极限
You get back 0 and 0 whether you go from the left or right, and Limit itself also gives 0,
无论从左侧还是从右侧你都会得到 0 所以极限本身即为 0
so there’s no problem over here. Although you do have kind of a piecewise function,
所以 这里没有问题 尽管这是一类分段函数
it in fact has a very simple limit at 0.
事实上它在 0 点具有一个十分简单的极限
On the other hand, here’s an example where things can go wrong. If you divide
另一方面 这里有一个错误的例子 如果你
the real absolute value of x by x, then the plot shows that you clearly have a kind of jump over here
如果你将 x 的绝对值函数除以 x 那么图像将会有明显的跳跃
because when you are at the right, the answer is 1, and when you are at the left the answer is −1.
因为你的右极限为 1 而左极限为 -1
The left-hand limit is −1, the right-hand limit is 1, and hence the limit does not exist.
左右极限不相等 因此极限并不存在
That’s a jump at a single point, but of course things can get much worse.
函数在单点发生跳跃 然而情况可以变得更糟
Here is the so-called floor function. The floor function will calculate the greatest integer
这是所谓的阶梯函数 阶梯函数给出最大的整数值对于
less than or equal to x. The problem is to find where the limit does not exist
对于小于等于 x 问题是找出在哪些点极限不存在
in the range from −2 to 2. Here’s a plot, and it’s clear that you have an issue at all the integers.
在区间 −2 到 2 可以从图中看出在所有整数点处都是有问题的
They jump at every place. For example, at 0 you have the left-hand limit is −1
所有整数点处函数都有跳跃 例如 在 0 点左极限为 -1
and the right-hand limit is 0, so the limit does not exist. In fact, I can confirm that
而右极限为 0 所以极限不存在 事实上可以证明
at every integer between −2 and 2, you have no limit existing. All the limits are indeterminate.
在 -2 到 2 之间的所有整数点处 极限都是不存在的 所有这些点的极限都是不确定的
The floor function is an example of a function which has no limit at an infinite number of points.
阶梯函数是一个函数在无穷多点极限不存在的例子
Now in practice, if we have a very complicated function like the one over here,
现在实践中 如果我们有一个非常复杂的函数
then what you can try and do is to kind of squeeze the function between two simpler functions.
你可以试着将它限制在两个更简单的函数中间
A little more abstractly, if you have a function g and that function g lies between f and h
更抽象一点 如果你有一个在 f 和 h 之间的函数 g
and you know the limits of both f and h, then you also know the limit of g.
并且 f 和 h 的极限都已知 那么你也就得到了 g 的极限
With the function over here, you can see quite clearly that the cosine is going to go
对于这个函数 你可以看到余弦函数处于
between −1 and 1, so you could pick f to be x^2 and pick h to be −x^2.
-1 和 1 之间 你可以选择 f 为 x^2 选择 h 为 −x^2
That’s going between −1 and 1. You’ve got f, you’ve got g and you’ve got h. g is the complicated one,
介于 -1 和 1 之间 已知 f g 和 h. g 是最复杂的
and if you plot them, you see that g is tightly squeezed between f and h near 0.
如果把它们全部绘制出来 你可以看到 g 在 0 附近严格地被夹在 f 和 h 之间
g is this wiggly function over here, and it’s very tightly squeezed. The squeeze theorem says that
g 是这儿的上下波动的函数 并且紧密的夹在中间 两边夹定理说
you can work out the limit of g provided that you can find the limits of f and h.
如果你能得到函数 f 和 h 的极限 那么 g 的极限就能得到
But f and h are simple. They’re polynomials, so their limits are just 0,
然而 f 和 h 的极限十分简单 他们是多项式 所以 他们的极限为 0
and hence the limit of g is 0 as well.
因此 g 的极限也是 0
Okay. That brings me to the end of today’s lesson, and I’ll summarize by saying that
好 今天的课程到此结束 我来总结一下
the limit laws give us a way to find the limits of functions mathematically.
极限法则给了我们一种数学上求函数极限的方法
You can use tables for sure, but the limit laws are the best ways to get the limits of functions.
你当然可以使用极限表 但是极限法则是计算函数极限的最好方式
There are laws for sums, for differences, for products and for quotients. Now from these laws,
从和 差 积 商 的极限法则
you can work out the law of finding limits for any polynomial. That’s really simple,
你可以得到多项式的极限法则
but it is somewhat harder to find the limits of rational functions which can become 0
但是会遇到一些困难在算有理函数的极限时 他会有 0
in the denominator at some point or piecewise functions where things can go quite wrong, et cetera.
出现在分母上在某些点处 或者对一些分段函数甚至会更加糟糕 等等
Finally, the squeeze theorem is a great way to find limits when you are given difficult functions
最后 当你遇到一些求极限比较困难的函数时 两边夹定理是求极限的一种好方法
which can be squeezed between simpler functions. This is about today’s lesson,
可以选择简单的函数来夹逼求极限 这就是今天的课程
and the next lesson, we’ll cover continuous functions, which will make life much easier for us
下节课 我们会讨论连续函数 这会使我们求极限的过程更简单
as far as finding limits are concerned. But before that, we will have a problem session
不过在此之前 我们会有一个习题课
to discuss various problems which relate to the material covered so far. Do review today’s lesson,
来讨论一些与已经讲过的内容相关的问题 务必复习今天的课程
go over the examples, the exercises and try and figure out how you might proceed
复习一下例子和练习，并试着
by trying things on your own and mastering the area. Thank you very much. I’ll stop here.
自己试验并掌握这些知识 非常感谢 我就讲到这里
(翻译: 秦晋 北京师范大学)
(校对: 周怀尚 兰州大学）